of the Future Money Podcast. Before we start, first of all, I'm happy to start to 2024,
but I want to say again, a big thank you to the half million of you following my content
each week. This podcast, The Future Money, is now again, once again ranked in the top
5% of all podcasts globally on Spotify. There's thousands of you every week from over 160
countries listening to this show. So a massive thank you for all your support. As you all
loyal listeners know, my goal with the podcast is very simple. It's to go deep in some of
the biggest ideas, trends and developments we're seeing in the field of crypto and hopefully
empower you with this information and then let you make your own decision on what their
impact can be on the future of money and the future of finance. And to do this, I invite
each week one of the leading figures of the global financial and crypto community to have
this one-on-one conversation. And our special guest today is someone I think many of you
are now have heard, and I've seen him speak around TV or different mediums. As Mr. Jake
Clayton, the former chair of the SEC from 2017 until 2020, who is now a senior policy
advisor and of counsel at Sullivan and Cromwell. Jake Clayton, welcome to the show. Good to
have you on the future Money podcast. Thank you and happy new year. Exactly. Well, one
thing, by the way, many many of our audience may know you as a former SEC chair, but one
fun fact about you, many people don't know is apparently you're a big open, open ocean
swimmer. And you're brave enough to even go in the shores of Jersey in the summer months
that we have. So here you go. One fun fact about who said ex-regulators are boring people,
you know? Here you go. Well, thank you. And, you know, I got to love the Jersey shore.
I also said, by the way, in your bio, you used to play soccer back in a day in rugby,
apparently, in your university days. Yeah, you wouldn't know it to look at me, would
you? So, actually, let's get going with that, Jay. I mean, obviously, he's been now some
time through four years, you're not at the SEC. How has life changed for you? On a personal
level, are you finding life and private practice easier than the good old regular regulator
days? Like, tell us more about how, on a personal level, life has changed for you in the past
couple of years. Well, you know, I don't think I can really look at it as how life has changed.
Having the privilege to have a regulatory job, like chair of the SEC or chair of one
of the other US regulators or, say, another G7 financial regulator, it's such a special
experience, particularly for somebody who cares about markets, cares about investing,
wants to see, in America, in particular, middle-class investors benefit from, you know, our capital
markets and investment. I try to compare it, but the longer time goes by, the more I realize
I can't. And that doesn't mean I'm not super happy. You know, I'm happy with what I'm doing.
I like advising clients. I like the boards that I sit on. I like doing those things.
But it is a, I think the more time goes by, the more I look at it as a special time, including
because of the people I work with. I had the most fantastic team.
It's amazing. And it's interesting that it changes. It's a privilege to serve, like
you said, right? It has actually people often underestimate, especially those who are not
lawyers or have not followed the regular scene. The impact that a regulator like the SEC has
on the, not only middle class, but the investing public on large, not only in the US, but also
globally as well, like that the power that is given and the impact you have is something
that is quite incredible, actually.
Can I give you just one stat that I hold, dear? And that is, if you look at fines that
the SEC and financial remedies that the SEC collects every year and it's high watermark.
We had, you know, we had pretty high fines when I was there. I hope they were good fines,
but $4 billion, $4 or $5 billion. If you look at the middle class money in the market, let's
just take a really low estimate. It's probably $10 trillion. If you say 50 basis points, half
a percent a year because you've reduced costs, you've been more efficient, you've been more
observant. That's $50 billion. More than 10X, the fines that get all the publicity, you
can put in people's pockets just by adding efficiency. Isn't that amazing? Yeah. I think
that's the kind of power you could have. You could do your job well as a regular.
Well, actually, before we talk about crypto on this topic, right, I mean, when you look
at the SEC, the SEC Chair in 2050 or the SEC Chair in 2070, how do you think the regulator
of the future will look like? Is it actually the, will it be still lawyers or somebody with
regulatory background, you think? Or it'll be skills like AI technology will be more
in demand. How do you see that Jay Clayton in 2070 or the, you know, who's the SEC Chair?
How would he or she look on that side? You know what? That's the first time in this
type of forum, someone has asked me that question and it's a fabulous question because our markets,
our markets are going to change. Traditionally, there's been a dichotomy between public and
private investments. And there's, there's been a big dichotomy between retail investors
and institutional investors and a big dichotomy between onshore U.S. investments and the rest
of the world. Technology, the speed, all of those things are going to collapse those right
distinctions that we've had over time. And the regulator of the future, the regulator
of the next five, 10, 15 is going to have to deal with that. What I would say is merging
of silos and do it efficiently. So I think it is going to require someone who has either
the skills themselves or is able to attract the skills around AI technology and the like.
Things aren't going to change. And the question is also where do you get the skills and not
to do all too much on this? But I still find it incredible that we let law students, for
example, graduate from law school with no courses on coding. You know, if we believe smart contracts
will be a big topic or you know how to use AI in enforcement cases, for example, and so
on and so forth. I think there's also the educate, even bar exams, you can argue, are
we testing the rights? Let me tell you something we're going to have to lose. We're going to
have to lose this aversion to the quote unquote revolving door. If we're not bringing people
who are working in technology, working in markets in the private sector into our regulators,
we're going to whiff on the future. You cannot become adept at these skills inside the government
of today because government is behind on technology. And you think what it changes required? Again,
the government is behind when it comes from a technology perspective. What do you think are
changes are needed? Is it a fundamental change? Is it a mindset? Is it skillset? I think it's a
mindset understanding what what I just said. I hope I hope you agree if you disagree, let me
know. But the idea that the technologists inside the government in our most core functions are a
generation behind the technologists in the private sector. That's not sustainable for good
government operation. I mean, our IRS is still using paper. We don't need 75,000 new IRS agents.
We probably need 20,000 less and a thousand who really know how to apply AI to the review of
tax returns. We will do better adopting AI and tax return review than we will hiring another 50,
75,000 people. There's no doubt about it. Think about just that example. 100%. I think it is a
whole skillset mindset, like I said, the generation even behind is probably very polite and diplomatic
of you as well. But I think there's a lot of there's a lot of work that needs to be done for sure.
Why does the U.S. stand where it does in terms of markets and economy? Post World War II, we brought
a lot of people, including during World War II, we brought a lot of people with a lot of real world
corporate experience into the government. And we set up and we set up functions that to be to be
blunt, we've relied upon for the last 15 years. Yeah, exactly. So let's talk about that from a
U.S. competitiveness perspective, right? What digital assets, for example, right? Right now,
when we look at crypto, you know, in during your tenure, obviously you took a very active role when
it comes to going after ICOs that were being sold as securities, all the way to think it was your
last day in office where you had the ripple case that was filed. And obviously, those were really
the the hoopla hoopla days of crypto, literally, I especially the ICO boom, there was obviously a
lot of scams and a lot of bad apples that gave the industry a bad name. Wouldn't you look at it now
taking a step back of let's say the U.S. crypto digital assets regulatory framework, right? And
you talk to clients around the world. Where do you think we stand from a U.S. perspective? Do you
think the U.S. has missed a bonus behind? Do you think this approach of regulation by enforcement
is the way to go? Just to get your general thoughts on where the U.S. stands on a policy
perspective. Yeah, I find particularly in a capital raising area, but I'm going to go a little deep
here. There are two types of securities transactions. And let me be clear, we regulate securities
transactions, not securities themselves. There are two types of securities transactions we regulate
in U.S. The first is capital raising transactions. The ICOs, when someone is saying, here's a token,
here's a security, here's a bond, here's an in exchange for your money, I'm giving you that,
and it's going to increase in value of my venture goes with. We in the U.S. rigorously regulate
those transactions if they're public. So if you go out to the general public and raise money,
you have to jump through, I would say, immense. I would say incalculable hurdles for anything
other than a large company. Now, is that a good policy decision? Maybe yes, maybe no,
but that's at the core of our securities laws. And I think the ICO folks and others just didn't
understand how fundamental that rigorous regulation of capital raising is. The second
type of securities transactions are trading transactions. Once the capital raising function
has settled, and let me just be clear, a company sells to me and then I sell to you the next day,
that's still part of capital raising. A couple says to me, I hold it for a while,
it comes, I've had economic exposure to it, and I sell to you six months later,
that's a secondary transaction. We regulate that very differently depending on how that
transaction takes place. I hold a security for a year and I sell it to you, no exchange involved,
no broker involved, we're just trading, there is really no regulation. Then there's platforms
that are lightly regulated in terms of a lot of bonds and other things trade on those platforms,
and then the highest form of regulation is exchange type regulation per secondary trading.
So it's quite complicated, and what happened with crypto was in both those types of transactions,
people just thought the technology could let them blow through respect for those spaces.
As this plays out, I think people have realized capital raising is going to continue to be
regulated, and now we're going to find our way on trading depending on what type of transaction it
is, and whether the capital raising token has remained a security or not. So I just said a whole
lot, but I hope it was somewhat clear. Absolutely, but let's go a bit layer deep on this.
So let's go ahead, you mentioned obviously the issuance and the trading, right?
On the issue inside, if we know we asked the brother of crypto community today,
there's obviously a lot of skepticism, but also frustration on because obviously we don't know
whether these assets are security in the first place, right? And the characterization of it.
I know you've been public saying Bitcoin is probably not a security, but of course the ACCS
taken this ambivalent position with a number of other digital assets. Do you think this lack of
clarity is actually a problem, or do you think it's fixable or is just inherent way legislation is
drafted and operates in the US that it's going to continue this way for a while?
I don't think there's very much lack of clarity. I think if you look at the substance of what
people are selling, you can pretty easily ascertain whether the transaction involves what we would
classify as a securities transaction, which is I give you my money in exchange for something.
And I'm expecting that something, whether it's a token, a bond, I'm expecting that
something to increase in value due to your efforts. Now, I love to give this. Can I go into an analogy?
Of course, go ahead. It shows the distinction. You come to me and you say, you know what, Jay,
I have a fabulous idea for a Broadway production. I don't know if it's going to work, but it could
be huge. If I get a great music score, if I get a great set of actors, if I get a great venue,
we're going to produce something and it's going to be about the circle of life on the savannah and
Africa. And you say, Jay, hey, give me $10,000 and I'm going to give you 10,000 tickets.
Those tickets might be worth, today they're worth a dollar, maybe, but they might be worth
$100 or $1,000 each in five years. Those tickets represent a securities transaction.
You've told me you're going to build out this play and in 10 years, these tickets may be worth
something. That's a securities transaction. 10 years later, you've produced this play.
It's selling out every night. I walk up to the box office and buy a ticket. It's just a ticket.
It's for the show. I'm not buying it expecting you to do more and increase in value. I'm not buying
it to finance you. I'm buying it to go to the show. And you can see how something that takes the same
form can be something different 10 years ago than it is today. People use that transformation
to argue that at the fundraising level, when there's no venue, no actors, no nothing,
it's still not a security. Give me a break. You're buying it. You're buying it. Hopefully,
you're going to do a great job. I want you to do a great job. And I might even sell to my neighbor
saying, "Hey, you know." I mean, the argument there would be, I get it, your analogy with
a ticket that it's, you know, you buy $10,000, $10,000 tickets at $1. I guess the way the debate would be
if you're selling this membership that lets you access the Broadway venue, you know, that becomes
more memory. I guess that's where the nuances are coming in. You can dress it up. But once you make
that membership transferable, it sure doesn't look like I'm buying a membership. It looks like I'm
buying something hoping you build a great club that all the fantastic stars come to afterwards.
And these kinds of, what I would say is these kind of semantic games around securities regulation,
they're not new to crypto. I could tell you that I spent my life as a securities lawyer with people
coming to me with these ideas. I was like, "Nope, it doesn't work." But the argument on this,
you know, is the argument again, obviously there's this situation which we are in the US right now
where a lot of these tokens, obviously there's all the litigation went on with the SEC. But then
let's say if a crypto exchange wanted to register, the second point, you mentioned issuance and
you mentioned trading, right? An exchange would come and wants to register, for example, to trade
securities. It is in practice, according to a lot of these exchanges, the fact though impossible,
right? So that's whether the the limbo a lot of these crypto exchanges are in right now,
which calls difficulty as well. This is where there is valid questioning. And I'll even go so far
to say valid, valid criticism that to the extent this technology is a new way to raise capital,
new way to facilitate trading, the regulatory community has been slow to embrace it.
You know, if I walk in to a regulator and say whether this is or is not a security,
let's end that debate, let's treat it like it's a security, what do I have to do
to facilitate trading initiatives? That's that's a question that should be being answered.
And I think if there was a rule, there was an option being regulated, obviously the
one that one of those problems would go away. Can I just say, can I just say this?
Not that sympathetic to the frustration that we have rigorous securities laws. I am sympathetic
to the frustration that we have not adopted those laws to allow the new technology in.
So, you know, for a technologist, if a technologist comes to a regulator and says,
look, this technology complies with all of your regulations, does your regulatory job at least
as well, but is more efficient. People get the information, they get the protections,
they get all those things, and it's more efficient. A regulator should embrace them.
One of the problems was technologists came and said, this technology is so good,
we should ignore some of those pesky regulations and you should adopt it anyway.
That's never going to work with a regulator.
So, if you have, let's say, a message of feedback or general advice to the crypto community,
do you think over the years a crypto community took the right approach in dealing with regulators,
where we took cocky, where we threw arrogant or it was a bit naivety when it came to regulatory
matters and what advice would you give to the crypto community in the way they're dealing with
regulators? I think they were two mistakes by the crypto community. The first was to think that
the principles of financial regulation and spheres regulation were going to change
as a result of technology. I don't think that was ever going to happen. We have too much vested
interest in the protection of our retail investors and rightfully so, the ICO boom shows why you need
for $4 billion up and slowly. The second thing was, once that was realized that the law was not
going to bend substantially, to go for comprehensive legal change, rather than incremental change,
was another mistake. My advice has been, start with something simple, it's proven like stablecoin.
Figure out how to get a well functioning stablecoin. Figure out how to custody digital assets,
whether it's a digital commodity, a digital security or something else. Let's figure out how to
custody them. Then let's figure out how to, if we take those incremental steps, we're going to get
somewhere. The idea, the myth that there was going to be great legislative change that was
going to revamp the securities markets, the commodities markets, create a new regulator,
that was crazy. It's interesting because obviously, and I know you wrote opeds about this topic,
about your views on stablecoins, and I agree with you, there's a lot of benefits that stablecoins
can provide. I hear you where you mentioned that stablecoins, sorry, it's an easy, it's an
layup that actually community could use because of the benefits are there. But the crypto community
too is defense. There's been numerous efforts to try to provide, obviously, the stablecoin rails,
and there's numerous attempts to do. Obviously, I'm not talking about algorithmic stablecoins and
some of the scams out there, but on a properly regulated manner, do you still hold the same view
that obviously stablecoins have a lot of potential? What do you think could be done to bring stablecoins
more mainstream if that's a goal that you believe from a policy perspective we should have?
I think stablecoins have immense potential. I think we should facilitate truly stable
stablecoins in our ecosystem. The amazing amount of stablecoin transactions that have taken place
without a single complaint that I know of instantaneously across the globe. Are you kidding me?
Remarkable. We should facilitate that. Why has it taken so long? People have asked for much more
than just that as a start. You're talking to regulators and you're talking to legislators
that have limited bandwidth. If you're coming at them with 10 asks and eight are unreasonable,
they're not going to filter out the two that are reasonable. They're just going to look at this
crypto community in a monolithic way and say that's just too hard. That's the reality of the
bandwidth in the legislative process and bandwidth in the regulatory process is limited.
It comes back to what you mentioned before. We should have
incrementally basically go for these baby steps, baby wins, and maybe stablecoins are one way to
achieve that. I think the Bitcoin ETF, which I do believe will be approved, I think that
for the adoption of distributed ledger technology tokenization and the like across the financial
ecosystem, this is way underestimated. The SEC is if the SEC approves these, that means they've
gotten comfortable that the custody of digital assets works. That the create and redeem function
around digital assets works. That the trading of digital assets that are not securities is
sufficient that they can feel comfortable. That's a big step forward.
Obviously your view is that actually a physical ETF will be approved, you believe in first quarter,
I mean 2024, January, 2024, if you're a betting man. So I don't own any and I don't bad necessarily,
but what I think is every legal issue and I think every functional issue has been decided
around Bitcoin and an ETF. So I've said and I'll say here, I think it's inevitable.
I don't know what hurdle is left to clear.
So why do you believe it took so much time? Was it because it's inherent of hurdles?
Let's say how we know that the redemption is working, the subscription is working,
like the custody issues. Do you believe those were the issues or do you believe it was more?
Many would say there was lobbying from some of the institutional players who were not ready yet.
Many would say there was just the SEC and the anti-crypto approach that was taken.
What do you think it took so long for the physical Bitcoin ETF to be approved?
If it's one of the tools. Multiple issues. And look, I was there when the first
applications were filed. Looked at the trading market for Bitcoin. It was global. It had
very few controls. There was obvious manipulation, whether it was wash sales,
laddering, pump and dumps, all sorts of the kinds of activity that as a regulator, you have to ask
yourself, should we have retail exposure to a market where we know there's fraud?
Now, the underlying trading in Bitcoin through work of actually private institutions
is at a what I would say is at a level of surveillance, at a level of volume and the like,
where institutional investors, sponsors have come in and said, we're putting our good name
behind us. We think these markets are actually functioning with minimal or no manipulation and
fraud. So that's a sea change. And I think that that's an appropriate hurdle that a market has to
get over before you're going to have a retail product available for that disclosure. And then
the mechanics, the custody, the creator deed, that all of those things work and to put a point on it,
hacking and other types of risks that we saw are not there. Lastly, and I think this is a book that
the asset itself, the underlying asset itself, is not being used for nefarious purposes.
And the amount of AML, KYC, BSA, that goes on in this market around the globe has increased
dramatically. So all of those things are changes. So people can look back and say, oh, oh my gosh,
it took too long. But take each one of those things and say, when we're really comfortable with this.
Yeah. Interesting point. You mentioned, of course, I think the, I agree with you on the,
when it comes to elements like custody, there's been obviously tremendous comfort and improvements
that have been done by the crypto community. You know, where, not to be the devil's advocate,
but many would say, okay, when it comes to levels of fraud. And I think there will always going to
be any asset class in crypto, there will always going to be a level of fraud and bad actors.
But if we're, let's say, we're comfortable with, I mean, right now there's ETFs on markets like,
like, I don't know, India, China, Philippines, or other smaller countries or other assets where
you could argue the level of corporate governance, for example, is not as high, but we're comfortable
with that, whereas with Bitcoin, we were not. And to be fair, like I think you mentioned very
clearly, the level of nefarious activity and digital assets is significantly lower than what many
would believe in the in the broader public. And this point, you know, Chuck Layton, you mentioned,
for example, the, the, the, the low, low level of nefarious activity when it comes to digital assets.
And I think the data proves it. And we should see how actually, yes, there's always people using
crypto for bad things. I think that's going to continue for years to come in the same way that
cash is using other things are used as well. But why do you think from a political perspective,
let's say, Congress, those arguments that crypto is being used mainly from bad actors and terrorist
organizations is still the kind of the headline that is being advocated or put forward.
Look, when let's, let's be, let's just be pragmatic. When, when labels stick,
even when they no longer are appropriate, it's very difficult to peel them off. Now, you know,
one, one that, you know, you hear all the time and you regulation by enforcement.
That's a label that has stuck to the regulatory community. Another way to say it is enforcement
of regulations. The regulations haven't changed. The, the SEC has won virtually every case.
You know, it's enforcement of regulation is at least as good a mantra. The same thing I think has
happened with crypto. You know, crypto is dark web. It's nefarious. It's, it's these types of things.
That may have all been cleaned up. But peeling that label off and replacing it with, no, no,
crypto is the most traceable asset. It's, it's, it's, it's on an immutable ledger. You know,
if you have a problem, it's cash. You know, but, but shifting from one label to another in a
politically charged emotional atmosphere, never easy. Maybe crypto. We have also, I think a PR
problem and marketing problem, branding problem that needs to be, that needs to be addressed as
well. One last question. I just want to get your views on the, on the international element as
well. One last point you mentioned casewids, right? Of course, your last filing, the last case
before you left was against Ripple. Any thoughts you have on how the court judgments came out of
Ripple? Obviously, there was kind of a mitigated with some ones for the SEC and some others for
XRP and, and, and, and, and Ripple, like, what's your view on it? Looking back at it right now,
like two, three years after you left office. Well, the way the court is now, and this is a,
this is a case that has not been finally resolved. There are appeals and the like. But if you look at
the distinction I made at the beginning of our discussion between securities transactions that are
for the purpose of capitalism, where I said we have very rigorous regulations, and then securities
regulation for secondary trading, you look at what the court did, it said, Hey, that capital
raising transaction is a securities transaction. Now, the court found that the secondary trading
transaction and its definition of secondary trading transaction was not. We'll see how that
goes on appeal. We'll see how both of them go on appeal. Yeah. But the, the point I want to make
is that we rigorously regulate the rate of the raising of capital from the general public,
and that has not changed. Yeah, interesting. So let's talk about a little bit of international
perspective. You know, obviously when you're in the SEC, you're involved in many international
organizations and associations, regulators from IOSCO to others. You know, over the years,
and we discussing at the initial, at the first part of our chat about the regulator or the future,
and what the future regulator will look like. When you look at regulators internationally today,
what regulators or countries or policy bodies, you think have done a good job or they have done a
good job in embracing technology and change, and its practical impact on the public?
Let me put it this way. I think that where you are, Abu Dhabi Dubai, they are looking at what we
were just talking about. Are there ways to use technology such that we don't need such a stark
dichotomy between offerings to the retail public and the types of things that are sold to institutional
investors? Like I said, I'm sympathetic to the frustration that our regulation is so rigorous.
Are there ways that we can use technology where we can take away some of those hurdles but still
have the same level of effective investor protection? I think some people are starting to think about
that, but we really do need to bring new technologists into the regulatory ecosystem to make that
visionary reality. Absolutely. Actually, you mentioned Abu Dhabi and Dubai. Actually,
where I'm sitting right now in Dubai, there was the world's first crypto specialized regulator,
the virtual assets regulatory authority of Vara for short. Do you think that one of the things that
we will see regulators do in the future is specializing in a very good Vara in this case,
or you could argue back in the day with the CFTC in the US, but you think this level of having
specialized regulator, in the case of crypto, Vara and Dubai was the first one, but having a
specialty at the regulator level is something that is good that we may see in the future in other
jurisdictions. Here's my view. I think we are going to need specialists in technology
within all types of financial regulators, whether it's securities, commodities, banking,
or what I would say is central bank. All across the spectrum, we're going to need people who
understand the efficiencies that can be garnered from adding technology.
I actually see technology bringing these regulators together.
If you look at what actually happens in our financial system every single day,
securities transactions, commodities transactions, they're backed by payments.
Payments are backed by treasury securities. The ecosystem actually works every day across
these regulators, much to a much greater extent, and with much greater interdependence than we
recognize. As technology pulls together all of those different functions, those regulators are
going to have to get closer together. Interesting, huh? That actually some of these challenges and
technology could be the common denominator, actually, the conveyor in a way of selling them.
I think absolutely. Every securities transaction has a payment level.
The securities settlement and the payment level are quite separate. There's no reason why those
different transactions can't become more harmonious, shorter in time, less frictions,
probably safer, and less cost. Jay, maybe it's more of a personal question
based on your experience, but I've been a professor since for many years. I've been
teaching crypto and law schools and business scores and trade many regulators in central banks
around the world. One of my personal observations, I don't know what you think about it, but it was
often that it's very lonely at the top if you're a regulator. If I'm a normal person, quote-unquote,
I can go crypto meet up and ask a stupid question and nobody will care, frankly, with what I ask.
What I find on my own experience, that's why I publish books and a lot of regulators actually
listen to this show. They read my books or they go to my online courses because they want to learn,
but they cannot just ask. It's very lonely because obviously, I'm sure it was, I don't
know how it is when you're an SEC chair, but of course you have advisors, but it's still a small
circle of people that you're interested in. It's very lonely at the top. How did you address that
problem personally when you were there? How were you able to learn about new technologies and what
advice would you have to other policymakers and regulators who want to learn about some of these
new trends are coming up? I'll give you a general answer and then I'll ask and I'll answer about
the technology. The general answer was, I was very fortunate. I had a team and I could think of,
almost a dozen people just right off the top of my head who were not afraid to challenge me,
not afraid to say, "Jeg, that's not going to work," or I would go to them and say,
"What do you think?" That sense of loneliness at the top from a dialogue point of view,
I never really had that. I will say that when you run any organization, whether you're a CEO of a
company, whether you're running from a responsibility point of view, you wear it. It doesn't matter who
made the mistake, it doesn't matter if you did or it doesn't matter who, it's you own it and that's
just, if that makes you lonely, don't do the job because that's the reality. We just had some
presidents here at universities who lost their jobs, resigner, as I look at what happened,
the public didn't like that they wouldn't take responsibility for change at universities.
That's what the public was. These are good people, they're trying hard, but they missed on the
idea that when you're at the top and something goes wrong, it's your fault, it doesn't matter.
It's interesting how it works, absolutely. I think on that front and on the technology side as
well, like you said, it's important to be able to learn on this topic, but there's a lack of
responsibility with a lot of it. Do you think regulators though have not taken responsibility
in many cases, of the lack of progress? This is where the US turning over the government every
four years, the revolving nature, this is where we have a little bit of a problem because the
adoption and implementation of new technology cannot be done in a year, cannot be done in two
years. It has to be something that has planned out over time and it's only human nature that people
have a difficult time starting a project that they know they're not going to be able to finish.
I think that affects the longevity and timeline people have in mind from that perspective,
absolutely. Well, Jay, we're coming to the end of the show, I can't believe time flew so fast,
my bell is with me. So I'm going to ask you a quick question, I need one or two word answers
in my bell is here to keep us honest. Today, on this conversation, the bell is the chair of the
regulator. So he the bell decides I should have had a bell, but I'm probably handy in some of these
Congress hearings as well, I'm sure. So let's kick it off. What's you're at the SEC for a number
of years, what surprised you the most with being a regulator? The vast nature of our markets.
You mentioned your open sea swimmer. What's your favorite beach to swim in? Ocean sitting in
Jersey. Well, here we go, loyal loader from that side. You played a soccer in college. If
there is one team of any soccer football for international audience that you think was the
best soccer team ever, which one is it? The Arsenal team that never lost a game.
There you go. But Arsenal fans on the show. I'm sure you can't be out of the dream team.
What is the one scale you wish more people in the crypto community would have one scale,
more people in the crypto community should have patients? Oh, good one.
Sam Bankman feed gives you a call from why I don't worry is now. What's the one thing you tell
him, SDF? Reflect. Good one. If you could go back to university today, what is the one course you
would take that you wish that you wish I'd taken back in a day? Meteorology. Meteorology. Really?
Why is that? That's interesting. The weather, I see the weather every day and I wish I understood
it better. A 17 year old kid comes to you and says, Mr. Clayton, what topic should I study?
What degree do you recommend kids right now to get to be ready for the future?
A bias, a technical degree with the best professors at your university. Whatever technical department
has the best professors, take that. I love it. What's your favorite legal or regulatory movie of all
time? Oh, I think it's I think it's the opposite of legal and regulatory, the sting. You can't
police fraud unless you understand. I love it. If this is a tough one, I don't know how sensitive
it is. If you could be, tomorrow morning, the CEO of any regulatory body around the world,
not in the US, around the world, which way I thought you'd go be CEO of or chair?
The SEC. But I'm not going to do it again.
Very political there. Very diplomatic. What is the one advice you would give to anyone who's
entering the crypto space now? It's a technology. Find the product that at most
is like adopt that regulation and show people that your technology does it better.
There you go. There's another tricky one. You know, a 17 year old kid comes to you and tells
you, Mr. Clayton, I have these four job offers. Which one should I take? An investment bank,
a law firm, a startup, or working at the regulator? What job should he take as a first job?
17 year old, take the regulatory job. Really? Why is that? Because you'll see a lot. You'll get
to do a lot more earlier. And then in two years, decide whether you want to stay or do one of the
other three. Amazing. I love it. And the last question was Jake Clayton, the former chair of
the SEC and now a senior policy advisor of Council Sullivan, Cromwell. Mr. Clayton,
this is a traditional question that people call on my show. If you could have lunch or dinner with
one person that are alive, lunch or dinner with one person that are alive, who would you have lunch
or dinner with? That's so hard. Oh, gosh. Oh, yeah, there's so technology to government to sports.
You know, geez, I'm generally not stuffed, but that's a that's a stumper.
Um, um, it's tricky one. I know it's tricky one.
I think. Oh, I think Edison. Really interesting. Why is that? Great. I've never had that answer.
I love it. I think if we his inventions are still with us today.
Says it all. Exactly. Right. The state really stood the test at top. Our electric grid is
much the same as the electric grid he envisioned. Great answer. I love it. You know, I've asked this
question hundreds over years. The first time I get Edison, I love it. I also love the rationale.
I was Mr. J Clayton for my city chair. Thank you very much for being with us.
If people want to read about you, hear some of your thoughts. What's the best way they can
keep on top with Mr. J Clayton? Um, I think, uh, current, you know, CNBC podcast, you got five
minutes is all you can take. So there you go. And if you want to go, I've got more rigor. Look at
my speeches when I was at the SEC week. My team and I tried to to provide as clear a guidance as
as possible. Amazing. Well, thank you very much for being on the show for all your listeners.
Thank you. Hope you enjoyed this special episode with J Clayton again. Thank you for all the support
in the past year as well. And don't make sure to also subscribe to my YouTube channel. We can
see the video version of this podcast as well. A lot of other exclusive content. Thank you very
much, everybody. And that's see you soon for another episode of the future of money podcast.
Thank you very much.